Good morning. Today's daf is ע', Ayin, 70, and we are wrapping
up the refu'as in the Gemara here and going to actually get
back to the mishna in a little bit.
So I have a pain right here.
I have a pain right over there. Okay, so anyway, we pick
up here where the Gemara says, okay, sha.
לרוחשא, Leruchshasa, it is to what? The bottom of ס"ט עמוד ב',
Samech Tes amud bais, second wide line at the end. Okay, לרוחשא,
Leruchshasa, which is basically hemorrhoids or some other type of a problem
down there. ליתי אקיקא, Leisei akika, take acacia
wood, ועלוי, Ve'alva, aloe,
apparently, ואספירכא, Ve'aspircha, which now I don't even remember. I learned this.
Mercury. Right, right, right. Mercury, or Rashi actually says it's like raw
silver, which maybe is quicksilver. Okay. ומרתכא, Umirtacha, which is some type
of a silver dross, וחומסתא דפילון, Vechumseta defilon, and a little, a
little like a vial, a perfume vial, which was like they used
to hang around the neck of, which was a type of an
aromatic type of a mixture, a liquid.
ושיפא דחמימתא, Veshipa dechamimasa,
and gosh, I have to remember this.
They say dog excrement.
Oh right, thank you, thank you, dog excrement. וננקיט בשיחקי דכיתנא, Veninkot
beshachakei dechitna, and put it all together in like worn out cloths
of flax. בקיטא, Bekaita, if it's in the summer. ודאמר גופנא בסיתווא,
Ved'amar gufna besitva, or in a cotton in the fall, winter. Okay,
and I guess, I don't know what you're supposed to do once
you have it all wrapped up. Are you supposed to apply it
to that place? I don't know. Okay. ואי לא, Ve'i lo, and
if you can't do that or it doesn't work, לישקי שיכרא מרקא,
Lishkei shichra marka, drink a diluted beer. Okay. I'd go straight for
the diluted beer. Okay.
לשיגרונא, Leshigrona,
for now,
for, which is a thighs weakness or some type of an illness
on the thighs. All right, I think Soncino said hips, but sounds
to me like Rashi was saying thighs.
ליתי פסיא דמוניני, Leisei pasya demunini, get like a pot of a
fish. Rashi says, what does Rashi say?
Where's Rashi?
Yeah. כלי מלא ציר דגים, Kli malei tzir dagim, a fish of
like fish juice, fish brine. Right. וניקדר שישין זימני אהאי מתחלי, Venikdar
shishin zimni ahai matchasei, and rub it sixty times on one side
or one hip, ושישין זימני אהאי מתחלי, Vshishin zimni ahai matchasei, and
sixty times on the other. Okay.
לצמירתא, Letzamirta, for, which is, oh yes, a stone in the bladder.
ליתי תלת ניטופי משחא דכופרא, Leisei tlas nitufei
mishcha dechufra, is
it a kidney stone in the bladder?
It's going to the bladder.
Oh, so then I guess so. All right. All right. Better sense.
Okay. So, there you go.
Okay. So, take three
drops, ליתי תלת ניטופי משחא דכופרא, Leisei tlas nitufei mishcha dechufra, three
drops of like tar, of liquefied tar, ותלת ניטופי
אצרא דחרצי, Vetlas nitufei itzra decharzi, and three of leeks, three drops
of leeks, ותלת ניטופי דחמרא נקידא, Vetlas nitufei dechamra nekida, and three
drops of clear wine. ולישדי ליה לאיש באמה, Ulishdi lei l'ish be'amah,
and apply it for a man on his member, on his penis,
ולישא באותו מקום, Ul'isha b'oso makom, and in the same place for
a woman. ואי לא, Ve'i lo, if she's the one suffering. ליתי
אוזנא דזיקא, Leisei uchna dezika,
take an ear of a pitcher. וליתלי ליה לאיש באמה, Velisli lei
l'ish be'amah,
and suspend it on that place with the man, ולישא בדדין, Ul'isha
bedadin, and a woman on her, on her breasts. ואי לא, Ve'i
lo, and if that didn't work. ליתי חוטא דזהוריתא, Leisei chuta dezehurisa,
get a like purple string, דשזלתיה דומה בת דומה, Deshazaltesei duma bas
duma, that was woven, a spun by
a woman of ill repute, the daughter of a woman of ill
repute. וליתלי ליה לאיש באמה, Velisli lei l'ish be'amah, and suspend for
the man on the penis, ולישא בדדין, Ul'isha bedadin, and the woman
on the breast. ואי לא, Ve'i lo, and if that didn't work.
ליתי כינא דדכרא ונוקבתא, Leisei kina dedichra venukavta, get a louse of
male and female, I'm guessing taken from a man, taken from a
woman, and doesn't mean a male and female louse. וליתלי ליה לאיש
באמה ולישא באותו מקום, Velisli lei l'ish be'amah ul'isha b'oso makom, and
apply it in the genital area.
וכי משתין, Vechi mashtin, now, if
and when the man or woman has to urinate, נשתין אסיסנא יבשתא,
Nashtin asisna yaveshta,
they should urinate on like a dried thorn bush, בצינורא דדשא, Betzinora
dedasha, by the, by the door,
by the doorpost frame. ונעיין בחומסתא, Vena'ayein bechumseta, and you pay attention
with the stone, דנפיק מיניה, Denafik minei, that will emerge. Now, I
don't really get it because it's a stone, it's got to be
pretty darn small to get out through your when you urinate. דמעליא
לכולהו צמרא dema'alya lekulho tzimra
that would be that that will have you know health benefits for
all types of fever if you can if you get that stone.
Now לצמרא letzimra if you do have a fever לצמרא ברנא letzimra
barana an external fever, maybe it's something on the skin or something,
ליתי תלת גריבי סופלי leiti tlat grivei suflei get three like sacks
of of date pits ותלת גריבי אטרף אדרא vetlat grivei atraf adra
and three packs sacks of leaves of an אדרא adra tree. What
do they say an אדרא adra tree is? Alder? What? Alder? Okay.
Alder?
Okay. ונישקלינהו כחדא לחודא venishkalinhu kachada lechuda they are take each sack
separately. I'm sorry, ונישלקינהו venishlakinhu boil each sack
separately וליתיב בינייהו veleitib beineiyahu and sit between them I guess as
they're boiling ונינחנהו בתרתי מסקלי veninachnehu betartei masklei put them in two
baskets or two you know containers וליתי פתורא leiti patura and take
a table ולינח עילויה velinach iluvei and put the two baskets on
the table right one of these date pits and one of these
leaves וניקום עילויה venikum iluvei
and stand over over these baskets האי עילויה והאי לאו עילויה והאי
עילויה והאי לאו עילויה hai iluvei vehai lav iluvei vehai iluvei vehai
lav iluvei
stand over one and then sit down over the other or maybe
you know Soncino translated it as like bend down in front of
one and bend down in front of the other.
You're like inhaling them right and you're bending up and down but
also you're supposed to be breaking out a sweat as we see
because it says עד דנפיק ביה הבלא ad denafik beih havla until
you start sweating and ולסחי מינייהו velischi mineiyahu and then bathe yourself
from them I because it's boiled in water וכי שתי ממיא דאדרא
לישתי ממיא דסופלי לא לישתי vechi shati mimaya d'adra lishtei mimaya d'suflei
lo lishtei
and when you drink drink from the water of the אדרא adra
leaves you know mixture and not of the water from the from
the date pits משום דמיעקרי mishum demiakrei because it will cause it'll
cause one to become sterile. Okay. לצמרא גוונא letzimra gavna for an
internal fever ליתי שבע בוני דסילקא משבע משרי leiti sheva bunei desilka
misheva misharei take seven handfuls of דסילקא desilka
of beets משבע משרי misheva misharei from seven different beds you know
they grew in seven different rows ונישקלינהו בעפראיהו venishkalinhu be'afraiyahu and take
them with their dirt וניכול venechol and eat them. I hope not
with their dirt but okay maybe. ונישתי venishti אטרף
אדרא atraf adra בשיכרא beshichra and drink
now this אדרא adra leaf with with beer. Okay after you've eaten
the beets I guess. Okay או ענבי דתלא במיא דחזיזתא o invei
detala bemaya dechazizta
or drink I guess or drink or eat with beer grapes that
grew from a vine that grew around a you know that grew
around a palm tree that grew on water. All right. There you
go. Okay now לחזיזתא lechazizta for type of a of like a
sca- a skin lesion.
Like an anthrax?
Oh right like yeah something exactly like a חזיזתא. chazizta. Right. Okay
anyway so some type of a skin lesion ליתי שבע חיטי ארזניתא
leiti sheva chitei arzanita
take seven wheat stalks I guess of ארזניתא arzanita which is a
certain type of wheat stalk. Rashi says they're very kernels yes seven
kernels okay Rashi says it was very large type וניקלינהו veniklinhu
and burn them אמרחא חדתא amaracha chadta
on a new hoe and I guess use the metal of the
hoe as like the surface וניפוק משחא מינייהו venifok mishcha mineiyahu
and some liquid will will come out of them ונישוף venishuf and
rub it on I guess on the place. רב שימי בר אשי
Rav Shimi bar Ashi עבד ליה לההוא נכרי avad leih le'hahu nochri
so again we always have the I think it's constantly these it
was always the generation after Ravina and Rav Ashi that was trying
it out. Who before tried it out with the remember the stuff
with the 150 peppers? Was it also רב שימי בר אשי? Rav
Shimi bar Ashi? Hold on. Oh no רבין דמן נרש Ravin d'min
Narsh did it for the daughter of רב אשי. Rav Ashi. Now
רב שימי בר רב אשי Rav Shimi bar Rav Ashi the son
of רב אשי Rav Ashi עבד ליה לההוא כוכבי avad leih le'hahu
kochvi used this type used this ointment that came out of these
pieces out of these wheat kernels for a non-Jew לדבר אחר ledavar
acher for leprosy ואתסי ve'itsi and he was healed. All right. Now
אמר שמואל Amar Shmuel says Shmuel האי מאן דמחוי ליה באלונחיתא דפרסאי
hai man demachvi leih be'alunchita de'parsai a person that is pierced with
a Persian spear which apparently they tip the tip of it was
they put poison on the tip מחיה לא חיי mechiya lo chayei
will not live. אדהכי והכי ade'hachi vehachi but in the meanwhile while
you know in you know as you'll see maybe like you can
actually help him live a little longer he's gonna die but in
the meanwhile ניספו ליה בישרא שמינא אגומרי nispu leih bishra shamina agumrei
get some fatty meat on you know roasted on on coals וחמרא
חייא vechamra chaya and raw wine אפשר דחיי פורתא efshar dechayei purta
that might help him live a little bit longer.
Have a good last meal.
Exactly gotta die you might as well have some nice nice steak
first ומפקיד אביתיה umafkid abiteih it'll help him live long enough that
he can give instructions to his household you know give his last
will. will and testament. Okay, אמר רבידי בר אבין. Amar Ravidi bar
Avin. היי מאן, Hai man, by the way, you will notice that
now we have ended the entire long
anonymous version, which seems to have been emerging from Ravina and Rav
Ashi as we said, and now you're dealing with named statements, a
lot, much earlier, Shmuel than Ravina and Rav Ashi, and also the
the
you know, the tone is different, the style is different. היי מאן
ד-, Hai man de-, somebody who whatever, as opposed to like for
this disease do this, for this disease do that. And it's more
also like there's a little more narrative. Well maybe he'll live and
maybe whatever, you know, he'll have a chance to do that. So
clearly we're in like a different collection that was put together here.
Yes.
So Rashi lived a thousand years after all this vocabulary was common.
I was wondering that too.
How does he know what these words mean?
Must have been מסורת. mesorah.
I'm serious. Because we don't have earlier sources that informed Rashi, do
we?
You mean texts that he used? No, I think it was basically
מסורת. mesorah. מסורת? mesorah? Yeah, authentic. Yeah, I was wondering the same
thing, like who told Rashi what this strange word meant? Now, people
could say מן הדמיון, min hadimyon, but where did, but that doesn't
mean whether it's you know it's right or not, but where did
Rashi get it from? Right, there must have been a tradition. Yeah.
So these are earlier sources. It seemed the other sources were later
or they
just were, no that's what we said, it seems very, no no
no, could be, but it seems very clear from the Gemara we
read that all that anonymous stuff was Ravina and Rav Ashi because
Ravina and Rav Ashi were the ones challenged, then at one stage
Ravina said, no no but what Ravina was saying was what I
what I meant was X so it seems very clear. All right
so now the Gemara says like this, okay אמר רבידי בר אבין,
Amar Ravidi bar Avin, so said Ravidi bar Avin, היי מאן דבלע
זיבורא, Hai man devala zibora,
if somebody swallows a wasp, לא חיי, lo chaye, he won't live,
אדהכי והכי נשקיה רביעתא דחלא שמזג, adehachi vehachi nashkiei reviata dechala shamzag,
but in the meantime drink a רביעית, revi'it, like a few ounces
of vinegar, שמזג, shamzag, the name of a certain type of vinegar,
Rashi says it's very powerful, אפשר דחיי פורתא, efshar dechaye purta,
maybe he'll live a little bit
longer, ומפקד לביתיה, u'mafkeid l'beiteih, and have a chance to make your
arrangements at your house.
If you swallowed a whole insect you wouldn't live?
I don't know, I mean a wasp. Why if a wasp is
very hurtful when it stings on the outside, imagine what it's going
to do on the inside? I think that's the assumption. אמר רבי
יהושע בן לוי, Amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, said Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Levi, אכל בשר שור בלפת, achal basar shor balefat,
if somebody eats, now we're getting to as opposed to what to
do for, we switched also from possible curatives to things that would
give you a little extra time but you're definitely going to die
and now we're going to deal with more preventative medicine, right what
you can do to help not get sick in the first place
or to tell you the types of things that are going to
be dangerous for you. Okay. So a person that eats some beef,
בשר שור, basar shor, meat from an ox, בלפת, balefat, with a
turnip, ולן בלבנה, velan balevanah,
and sleeps outdoors in the moon, בליל ארבעה עשר ובליל חמישה עשר,
beleil arba'ah asar u'veleil chamishah asar, on the 14th or 15th of
a month when it's a full moon, בתקופת תמוז, bitkufat Tammuz, in
the summer months, okay, אחזתו אחילו, achazato achilu, is seized with achilu,
which we'll see how the Gemara describes but some type of like
fever or trembling. Okay. תנא, Tana, והממלא כריסו מכל
דבר,
vehamemalei kriso
mikol davar,
and if somebody just really stuffs his stomach with any food, so
if you overstuff yourself, אחזתו אחילו, achazato achilu, you're subject you might
get come down with this achilu. אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Pappa,
אפילו מתמרי, afillu mitamrei, even if you stuff yourself with dates. פשיטא,
Pshita, obviously we said with anything. No. סלקא דעתך
אמינא, Salka da'atach amina, notice the, we're back to more classic set
of Gemara types of discourse. We quote things, we discuss them. Anyway,
since the Master taught, הואיל ואמר מר, ho'il v'amar mar, תמרי משביען
ומשחנאן ומשלשלן ומאשרן ולא מפנקן, tamrei masbi'an umishachnan umishalshlan um'ashran velo mifankan,
that dates are so good, they cause you to be satiated
and they warm you up and they're good for digestion and they
give you strength and they don't spoil the
taste, so אימא לא, eima lo, maybe I think that dates have
this amazing property, they're a superfood, so maybe if you stuff yourself
with dates it won't be this problem? קא משמע לן, Ka mashma
lan, that even dates you might get come down with achilu. מאי
אחילו? Mai achilu? What is this achilu? אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar Rabbi
Elazar, אשת של עצמות, eshet shel atzamot, a fire of the bones.
What do they mean like heartburn?
Maybe you overeat and you get heartburn. Maybe,
but bones is funny. Anyway, maybe it means what's it called, arthritis.
Anyway, Seinfeld suggested that it's arthritis.
Okay, I don't know how stuffing yourself gives you arthritis but okay.
Anyway, okay I mean it sounds like right I mean it sounds
like it's a passing thing, you ate a lot then you're going
to get this like thing, it doesn't sound arthritis is
like the heavier you are
the worse your arthritis can be.
Oh really? Oh maybe.
Because the joints have to work harder to support the weight. Oh
that's interesting. Okay so but that's just okay. מאי אשת של עצמות?
Mai eshet shel atzamot? What's a fire of the bones? אמר אביי,
Amar Abaye, אשת גרמי, eshet garmi, a fire of the bones. So
go explain that. Okay. מאי אסותיה? Mai asuteih? What do you do
to heal this? I guess they didn't have Pepto Bismol. אמר אביי,
Amar Abaye, אמרה לי אם, amrah li eim, my mother said to
me... Mother meaning his nursemaid said to him, כולהו שקיאני תלתא ושבעא
ושתסרי. Kulehu shakyani tlata vesheva veshtasrei.
All types of medicines that you drink, liquid,
medicinal drinks, you either have to do them for three days or
seven days or twelve days. האי, Hai,
the treatment that you do for this, for this fire of the
bones, this אחילו, achilu, עד דמצלי, ad demitzai, you have to keep
up the treatment until it's fully healed. כולהו שקיאני, Kulehu shakyani, all
these types of things that you, these medicines that you drink, אליבא
ריקנא, aliba reikana,
you have to be on an empty stomach, literally an empty heart.
והאי, V'hai, but this one, no. Here's what you're going to do.
Here's when you're going to do the medicine. בתר דאכלי ושתי, Bat
d'achlei veshati, after you've eaten and drunk, ואייל לבית הכסא, v'ayel l'veis
hakisei, and then you've gone to the bathroom, relieved yourself, ונפיק, v'nafik,
you come out, ומשיי ידי, umashyei yedai, wash your hands, that's good,
avoid the germs. Okay. ומייתי ליה בונא דשסיתא, Umaysi lei buna deshasisa,
and they will take you
a fistful of שסיתא, shasisa, which is a type of a lentil,
something made out of lentil powder and salt, some type of a
porridge.
דטלפי, Detilafi, of lentils. ובונא דחמרא עתיקא, Ubuna dechamra atika, and a
fistful of old wine. ונגבלינהו בהדי הדדי, Venigblinu b'vadei hadadi, and you
knead them together. וניכול, Venichol, and you eat it. But you're eating
it on a full stomach, at least a full stomach after you've
relieved yourself. וניכרוך בסדיניה, Venichroch b'sadinei,
and then you wrap yourself in your blanket. וניגני, Venignei, and you
should go to sleep, okay? Because somehow you're going to... it'll cause
you to sweat and that'll be good for you, and we'll see
in... or you'll sweat it out, exactly. Or you'll get the chills
and you want to be wrapped up. Okay. וליכא דנוקמיה, Veleika de-nokmei,
and nobody should wake you up, עד דקאי מנפשיה, ad dekaymi nafshai,
until you just get up of your own accord. Let him sleep
until he gets up. וכי קאי, Veki kay, and when he does
get up, לשקליה לסדיניה, lishkeilei l'sadinei, he should
make sure to take his blanket away from him. ואי לא, V'ilo,
and if he doesn't, and if the blanket, I guess, stays... keeps
it on him even after he's woken up, הדר עלויה, hadar ilvei,
it'll come back to him, this illness. Okay. אמר ליה אליהו לרב
נתן, Amar lei Eliyahu l'Rav Nassan, so Eliyahu now is giving medical
advice, said to רב נתן: Rav Nassan: אכול שליש ושתה שליש, echol
shlish ushtei shlish,
eat a third of your fill, to fill up your stomach a
third, and drink for another third of your fill of your stomach.
והנח שליש, Vahanach shlish, like leave the table a little empty, don't
stuff yourself, similar to before. You know, if you stuff yourself with
anything, it's going to subject you possibly to this illness.
This is the change model, like you eat two-thirds of your satiety.
Really?
The רמב"ם Rambam says that too, not to eat until you're full.
Calorie restriction, like the... you know, they've said that in pretty much
every creature they've fed them like a bit less, like quite a
bit less than what they
need, they all live twice the lifespan.
Really? Even on humans, yeah, people are doing it on themselves.
Wow. Okay. לכשתכעוס, Lekhashtikhos, now his explanation is, because then when you
get angry, תעמוד על מלואך, tamar imluekh, your anger fills your belly.
So therefore then it'll fill your stomach. But if your stomach's already
full and you get angry, then that'll cause your stomach to burst
or cause you some obvious indigestion. Okay. But that's really interesting to
know that not eating your fill, you know, what, it's not just
good in the sense of like it keeps the weight down but
it's like just more general, you know.
They've tried it, I mean, you know, they haven't yet done it
on very long-lived species, they've done it on lower species.
And not eating your fill is that...
they, you know, I've read this, based on the science they think
people can live to 170 years.
170 years?
That's the maximum. Whoa.
Alright. Okay. תני רבי חייא, Tani Rabbi Chiya, Rabbi Chiya taught: הרוצה
שלא יבא
לידי חולי מעיים, harotzeh shelo yavo lidei choli me'ayim,
we're getting way, way back, right? We're getting now to the ברייתא
braisa level in terms of this. Somebody who wants to take steps
not to come to illnesses of the stomach, of the inner, of
the inner intestines, יהא רגיל בטיבול קיץ, yei ragil bitibul kayitz,
you should dip things in the summer, like in vinegar or oil
or whatever, וחורף, vechoref, and
in the summer
and in the winter. סעודה שהנאה הימנה, Seudah sheh-hana'ah mimenu,
and here again we get with not eating your fill, a meal
in which you're getting a lot of pleasure from, משוך ידך הימנה,
meshoch yadkha mimenu, withdraw your hand from,
don't eat your fill, hold back. ואל תשהא עצמך בשעה שאתה צריך
לנקביך, V'al tisha atzmekha besha'as sheh-atah tzarikh l'nekavekha, and don't hold yourself
back when you need to go to the bathroom, make sure to
take care of that immediately. Right. When you gotta go, you gotta
go.
That's also the רמב"ם, Rambam, he... yeah. Well, the רמב"ם Rambam gets...
yeah. I mean,
it is interesting. The רמב"ם Rambam generally says you can't trust the
רפואות, refuos,
the remedies in the גמרא, Gemara, but some of these things, I
don't know, it's interesting. A, they're earlier teachings, right? As opposed to
all of this which is very late and probably had, you know,
a lot of like Persian, Babylonian influence, stuff we did yesterday. And
right, and some of these actually can be understood as just general,
you know, good health types of advice as opposed to remedies which
seemed obviously a little bit more bizarre.
Do we know which רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya this is? Because there
are several רבי חייא'ס.
Rabbi Chiyas. I don't know. Okay.
Now, the גמרא Gemara had a lot of these stories and early
people that, you know, were... cut open. Yeah,
yeah, yeah.
The גמרא Gemara has a lot of things about not holding back
when you need to go to the bathroom. אמר מר עוקבא, Amar
Mar Ukva, said מר עוקבא: Mar Ukva: האי מאן דשתי Hai man
d'shati טילייא חיורא, tilaya khivra,
somebody who drinks this white inferior wine, אחזיהו
ויטק akhazihu Vitak is seized by this disease called ויטק Vitak which
we'll see about what it is in a minute. אמר רב חסדא:
Amar Rav Hisda: שיתין מיני חמרא הוו. shittin minei khamra havu. There
are sixty types of wine in the world. נעליא דכולהו, Na'alya d'khulhu,
the best, סומקא ריחנא sumka rikhana
is the red aromatic wine.
As in like healthiest?
I guess, I guess I don't know if it's healthiest or tastes
best but probably also healthiest because of what the context. גריעא דכולהו,
Geri'a d'khulhu, the worst, טילייא tilaya חיורא, khivra, this white inferior wine.
אמר רב יהודה: Amar Rav Yehuda: האי מאן דיתיב בצפרני ניסן, Hai
man d'yativ b'tziparnei Nissan,
somebody who sits in the mornings of ניסן Nissan of the spring,
גבי נורא gabe nura
by a fire, ושאיף משחא v'sha'if mishkha
and rubs himself with oil, ונפיק ויתיב בשמשא v'nafik v'yativ b'shimsha then
goes out and sits in the sun, אחזיהו ויטק akhazihu Vitak will
be seized by this ויטק Vitak disease, whatever it was. ותנו רבנן:
V'tanu Rabbanan: הקיז דם, hikiz dam, if somebody let blood, now again
we're in a ברייתא braita already and you could see it's all
also in Hebrew. הקיז דם ושמש, Hikiz dam v'shimmesh,
you let blood and then had sex, ושמש מטתו v'shimmesh mitato הוו
לו בנים ויטקין, havu lo banin vitakin, so
he has these children. Now it seems that this from the context
or whatever that this basically is a general type of a weakness,
this ויטק, Vitak, like it's some type of a, you know, just
causes basically a sapping of strength and a weakness. Just somebody does
this and this also goes to the גמרא Gemara as the גמרא
Gemara understands that certain things that were the circumstances when a child
was conceived, you know, about the man and the woman and what
was in their mind and what was going on in their body,
whatever, affects the nature of, you know, the child that's conceived sort
of reflects those realities. So after blood has been let, obviously the
person's strength is sapped, so the children will be, will be very
weak. הקיזו שניהם ושמשו, Hikizu shneihem v'shimmeshu, and if both of them
had let blood and they had intercourse, הוו להו בנים בעלי ראתן,
havu lehu banin ba'alei ra'tan, then they will be, you know, extremely
weak children. אמר רב פפא: Amar Rav Pappa: לא אמרן אלא דלא
טעים מידי, Lo amaran ela d'la ta'im midi, that's only if you
didn't eat something after they let blood, אבל טעים מידי לית לן
בה, aval ta'im midi leit lan bah, if they let something, ate
something after they ate blood before they had sex, that's not, won't
be a problem. And you know, right after you give blood they
give you something to eat, right? So okay. אמר רבא בר רב
הונא: Amar Rava bar Rav Huna: בא מן הדרך ושמש מטתו, Ba
min haderekh v'shimmesh mitato, if
somebody has sex right after they come back from a long journey,
so their body is like weary, right? It's very, it was very
trying on the body, these journeys. הוו לו בנים ויטקין, Havu lo
banin vitakin, same thing, the children will be, will be particularly weak.
ותנו רבנן: V'tanu Rabbanan: הבא מבית הכסא, Haba mi'beit hakisei, somebody who
returns from the bathroom, אל ישמש מטתו al yishamesh mitato עד שישהא
שיעור חצי מיל ad sheyishei shiur khatzi mil
until they wait the time it takes to walk basically half a
kilometer, which is not long, like ten minutes or something,
less actually. You walk a mile in like what, twenty minutes, and
a kilometer is what?
One kilometer is ten minutes. Ten minutes.
Okay, yeah, okay, so although the גמרא, Gemara, yeah, normally the basic
מיל mil is often assumed to be though like eighteen minutes, but
I guess, you know, you're walking slowly maybe, so half a מיל
mil would be like nine minutes.
Walking to the bathroom, you're walking.
All right, I get it. מפני ששיד בית הכסא מלוה עמו, Mipnei
she'shed beit hakisei melaveh imo, because the, now, now we're getting back
to the שדים, shedim, because the spirit, the שד, shed, the demon
of the bathhouse, accompanies you for a little while. So you don't
want to be having sex while that demon is attached to you.
Definitely an annoying assignment, but in the assignments of שד shed world.
ואם שמש, V'im shimmesh,
and if you but did have intercourse within that time, הוו לו
בנים נכפין, havu lo banin nikhpin, the children will be having, will
have epilepsy.
When they say like you know, חמירא סכנתא מאיסורא, khamira sakanta me'isura,
how much of this actually gets translated into normative הלכה? halakha? Because
these are really, you know, things about, oh.
Yeah, I mean, the רמב"ם Rambam was very selective on the ones
he thought were accurate. He basically thought the rabbis weren't doctors, so
you don't, it's not prescriptive, you know, just because it was uttered
by the rabbis and the ones he thought that actually were good,
the רמב"ם Rambam quotes. Yeah, most of this is not, if you
take a quick look at the הערה he'arah at the side, you'll
see there's basically none of it is quoted in שלחן ערוך. Shulchan
Aruch. To the degree any of it is quoted, it's quoted, it's
quoted selectively in the רמב"ם. Rambam.
But you have like, you know, בא מן הדרך.
ba min haderekh. I understand. Okay, תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. We just
did that. תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: המשמש מטתו מעומד, Hamishamesh mitato me'umad,
if somebody has intercourse while they are standing, אחזיהו עוית akhazihu avit
is seized by this עוית, avit, which is... רש"י Rashi says כרנפא,
karnafa,
I have no idea what that is. What did they translate it
as?
Nerve?
What? Spasms? Okay, cramps, spasms. Okay. מיושב אחזיהו דלייריא. Meyushav akhazihu delieria.
Okay. Actually, some have a גרסא girsa אולייריא, uleria, so
delirium would be delirium. How did they translate the second one? Delirium.
Delirium? All right. If somebody anyway has sex sitting down, fine. Then
they're, then, so this is not a הלכתי halakhic thing, this is
a health thing.
היא מלמעלה והוא מלמטה, Hi mil'malah v'hu mil'mata, if she is above
and he is below. below, או חזא סדלייריא o chaza sidulyaria also
this delirium. מאי דלייריא? Mai dulyaria? So it's interesting because there's other
גמרות Gemaras that also discuss questions about positions and also from a
sort of medical perspective but how that might affect how the kids
turn out. Here it's sort of how it affects your health. אמר
רבי יהושע בן לוי Amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi now what's delirium?
And the גמרא Gemara doesn't really answer it, but it tells you
what to do to treat it. סם דלייריא Sam dulyaria the healing
for delirium is דלדר. dardura. Do דלדר. dardura. מאי דלדר? Mai dardura?
What's דלדר? dardura? אמר אביי Amar Abaye מוריקא דחוחא morika dechuchei it
is some type of a saffron רש"י Rashi says that grows among
the thorns.
רב פפא Rav Papa לעיס ובלע ליה la'is uvala lei and says
you should chew it and swallow it. רב פפי Rav Pappi לעיס
ושדי ליה la'is ushadi lei I don't know it sounds personal though.
רב פפי Rav Pappi would chew it and spit it out.
You know I remember another גמרא Gemara says you know they were
talking about this, like you know this woman was complaining, remember this?
That she says like go
he's הפכיה hafachia remember this? She said אלוה כמשא. ala kumshei. Right.
So that's why I said this is
not הלכה, halacha, this is a health issue. אמר אביי Amar Abaye
מי שאינו בקי בדרך ארץ mi she'eino baki bederech eretz somebody who
is literally it's not expert in sexual intercourse but רש"י Rashi says
it means is like is too weak for it. ליתי גימל כפיזי
כורתמי דחוחא Leisi gimal kafizei kortamei dechuchei should take three כפיזים, kafizim,
three whatever, you know, measures of כורתמי דחוחא kortamei dechuchei which רש"י
Rashi says is, רש"י Rashi says it's again some type of something
that grows from ground that has been saffron, yeah, although it sounds
like רש"י Rashi translates this the same way as he does the
what do you call it, yeah. Okay anyway the saffron that grows
from ground that has been רש"י Rashi says that has particularly been
fertilized, thank you, with the excrement of sheep. Okay, and תוספות Tosafot
says
זה
כפיזי zeh kafizei is three-quarters of a לוג. log.
Okay, three-quarters of a לוג log of this saffron.
ונידקינהו venidkinhu and you should grind them ונישלקינהו venishlkinhu and boil them
בחמרא bechamra in wine ונישתי venishti and drink it. אמר רבי יוחנן
Amar Rabbi Yochanan הן הן החזירוני לנעורותי hen hen hechiziruni lenaaruti this
returned me to the strength of my youth.
That seems like a really expensive remedy.
Yeah, is it? Anyway רש"י Rashi says specifically it means in regards
to sexual intercourse. שלשה דברים מכחישים כחו של אדם Shlosha devarim machchishim
kocho shel adam three things weaken a person's, you know, general, you
know, strength. ואלו הן ve'elu hen and these are they not about
a certain illness but just about a general issue of health. ואלו
הן ve'elu hen these are they: פחד pachad which רש"י Rashi basically
says in the context anxiety, דרך derech going on trips,
why you shouldn't have
that right, ועון ve'avon and sin. Either the consequence of sin, and
then it's you know, or
תוספות Tosafot says, תוספות Tosafot says anxiety of sin. Okay,
so פחד דכתיב pachad dechtiv לבי סחרחר libi scharchur my heart has
like fluttered עזבני כחי azavani kochi my strength has abandoned me. So
we have פסוקים pesukim again. Right, it's true, exactly. Now according to
פסוקים. pesukim. דרך דכתיב Derech dechtiv עינה בדרך כחי ina vaderech kochi
God has sapped my strength on the path my strength. עון דכתיב
Avon dechtiv כשל בעוני כחי kashal ba'avoni kochi my strength has been
has stumbled over through my sin. שלשה דברים מתיזים גופו של אדם
Shlosha devarim mattisim gufo shel adam three things also weaken or shatter
the body of a person. ואלו הן ve'elu hen these are they:
אכל מעומד achal me'umad if somebody eats standing ושתה מעומד vashata me'umad
and and or drinks standing ושימש מיטתו מעומד veshimash mitato me'umad and
has sexual intercourse standing. וחמישה קרובים למיתה יתר מן החיים Vachamisha krovim
lemita yoter min hachayim and five things
if you do them,
probably any one of them, I don't mean all three all of
them as we're going to see in a minute by a different
list, anyway, brings you closer to death than life. ואלו הן ve'elu
hen these are they. I assume that I don't know if that
means that literally that a person might die, but just means the
way they feel is, you know, they feel like that they're, you
know, at death's door. And these are they: אכל ועמד achal va'amad
שתה ועמד shata va'amad I'm sorry did I skip that? No. Yeah,
you eat and then you stand up. So as opposed to eating
while you're standing, you eat and you get up immediately. You don't
let the food settle. You drink and you get up immediately. הקיז
דם ועמד hekiz dam va'amad you let blood and get up immediately.
ישן ועמד yashan va'amad you sleep and I guess you don't take
your time getting out of bed, you know, you get out of
bed suddenly. שימש מיטתו ועמד shimash mitato va'amad and has sex and
stand up right away. שישה העושה אותן מיד מת Shisha ha'oseh otan
miyad met six if somebody does them they die right away. And
this clearly is going to mean what we see from the גמרא
Gemara if you do all six. Okay, ואלו הן ve'elu hen these
are they: הבא
בדרך וניסתייגע haba vaderech venistaye'a somebody who comes from the travel from
a trip and is wearied out, הקיז
דם hekiz dam and then lets blood ונכנס לבית המרחץ venichnas leveit
hamerchatz and goes into a bathhouse ושתה vashata then drinks ונשתכר venishtaker
and gets drunk וישן vayashan and sleeps על גבי קרקע al gabei
karka on the floor ושימש מיטתו veshimash mitato and then has sex.
So if you do all those things then they'll bring about death.
אמר רבי יוחנן Amar Rabbi Yochanan והוא שעשאן כסידרן vehu she'asaan kesidran
only if you did it exactly in that order. אמר אביי Amar
Abaye כסידרן מת kesidran met if you do it in that order
you die, שלא כסידרן shelo chesidran if you do those six things
but in a different not in that order, חליש chalish you get
weak. איני? eini? Is that really true? וההיא מאורת vehahi Me'orat this
woman by the name of מאורת Me'orat עבדא ליה לעבדא תלת מינייהו
avda lei le'avda tlat mineihu did three of these to her slave...
servant and he died? No, ההוא כחוש הוה hahu kachush hava he
was already of a weak constitution beforehand. Okay. שמונה shmonah רובן קשים
ומיעוטן יפה ruban kashim u-miutan yafeh there are eight things where a
lot of it is difficult, is bad for you, and a little
is good for you. Again, presumably health-wise, but we will see. Some
of them could be learned to be more sort of more general
moral or statements, but it seems that we're talking in a health
context. ואלו הן ve-eilu hen these are they: דרך derech going on
trips, okay, a little is good, a little exercise is good, too
much wears you out. ודרך ארץ ve-derech eretz sexual intercourse. So is
that a moral statement or is that just a health statement? דרך
ארץ derech eretz meaning sexual intercourse, right? עושר osher wealth, okay, again,
does that mean if you're too wealthy then you get too indulgent
in pleasures, right? Or is this just that actually when that's bad
for you, it's bad for you because
of your character, your morals, right? In what way are these things
bad for you? Okay, but a little wealth is good to be
able to have enough money to take care of your needs, to
have a little extra spending money that's good, too much wealth is
not good.
Because if you have too much wealth you won't learn תורה. Torah.
You won't learn תורה. Torah. Right. So,
I'm sorry, I just came back from two weeks ago we saw
with the kids Fiddler on the Roof on Broadway, right? So at
one stage, Tevye says, "I realize it's no great shame to be
poor, but it's no great honor either." But at another place, who
is it, the intellectual starts saying,
"Wealth is the curse of
humanity."
He says, "God,
strike me down with it!"
Anyway. All right.
ומלאכה u-melachah work, okay, a certain amount of work is good, too
much, I don't know what too much is. Shouldn't be a workaholic.
I guess everybody has a different interpretation of what too much work
is, right?
Okay.
יין yayin wine, ושינה ve-sheinah sleep, חמין chamin hot water, רש״י Rashi
says both for bathing and for drinking, והקזת
דם ve-hakazat dam letting blood. שמונה shmonah eight things ממעטין את הזרע
memaatin et ha-zara cause
there to be less semen. ואלו הן ve-eilu hen and these are
they:
המלח ha-melach salt, ורעב ve-raav famine, והנתק ve-ha-netek which is some type
of a skin disease,
בכיה bechiyah crying, ושינה אגבי קרקע ve-sheinah agabi karka sleeping on the
ground, וגדגדניות ve-gadgedaniyot which I forget what that is. What does it
say that is?
Eating coriander. Coriander.
גד השדה. gad ha-sadeh.
Oh, that's true. Okay. וכסוס. ve-chsus. Clover.
And here's a picture.
Okay. וכסוס שלא
בזמנה ve-chsus shelo bizmanah and וכסוס ve-chsus which is hops, right, we
had that yesterday. Hops not in their right time. והקזת דם למטה
כפליים ve-hakazat dam lematah kiflayim and if you let blood on the
lower part of your body, it's doubly bad as any one of
these. תנו רבנן tanu rabanan as it says in a ברייתא, baraita,
כשם שקשה למטה כפליים keshem she-kasheh lematah kiflayim the same way it's
doubly bad when it's at the lower part of your body, כך
יפה למעלה כפליים kach yafeh lemalah kiflayim when it's at the upper
part of your body it's doubly good. I don't know, doubly good
of bad things or doubly good than it normally... anyway, אמר רב
פפא amar Rav Papa למטה lematah below, means למטה מן הביצים lematah
min ha-beitzim below the testicles. למעלה lemalah above, means למעלה מן הביצים.
lemalah min ha-beitzim. So that's the dividing line. וכסוס שלא בזמנה. ve-chsus
shelo bizmanah. Now, hops not in their right time. תנא tana it
is taught, כשם שקשה שלא בזמנה כך יפה בזמנה keshem she-kasheh shelo
bizmanah kach yafeh bizmanah the same way they are difficult, they're bad
for the body when they're not in their right time, they're good
for the body in their right time. אמר רב
פפא amar Rav Papa זמנה zmanah the time is
תמוז Tammuz which is basically the summer. שלא בזמנה shelo bizmanah טבת
Teves the winter. ימי ניסן וימי תשרי yemei Nisan ve-yemei Tishrei the
spring and the fall, לא מעלו ולא קשו lo maalu ve-lo kashu
are neither good nor bad for the body. Okay, back to הלכה.
halachah. Yeah.
We can now recite ברכת התורה. Birkat HaTorah. Yeah, exactly.
There's several
places here they're saying that sleeping on the ground is not healthy.
Yeah.
And in
פרקי אבות Pirkei Avot
it says על הארץ תישן. al ha-aretz tishan.
That's a good point. Well, the פרקי אבות Pirkei Avot is sort
of saying that you should be prepared to live a life of
privation for the sake of תלמוד תורה. talmud Torah. It's not saying
that it's necessarily healthy to sleep on the ground. But you're right,
I mean, still holding... I mean when it says,
מים במשורה תשתה, mayim bi-meshurah tishteh, eat bread and drink water, it's
not saying that that's the healthiest thing for the body. It's saying
you should be prepared to live a life of privation for the
sake of תורה. Torah. Okay. Okay, back to the משנה. Mishnah. אמר
תנו גט לאשתי ושיחזהו קורדייקוס וחזר ואמר אל תכתבוהו amar tenu get
le-ishti ve-shachazehu kordaikaus ve-chazar ve-amar al tichtivuhu
write a get for my wife and then he was seized with
קורדייקוס kordaikaus and then he said don't write one, אין בדבריו האחרונים
כלום ein bidvarav ha-acharonim klum the last words do nothing, which is
a real I think a big חידוש. chiddush. It says we're not
even חושש choshesh for them. We can give his wife a גט
get even though he retracted. And she's going to be ודאי מגורשת
vadai megureshet even though, right, he... because to say don't write it
on the basis of what he says when he has this state
and he's not in his right mind, fine, but to say go...
go ahead and write it, you know, and don't be afraid that
it counts as a retraction, that's a bigger statement. So we're really,
we're taking it as a ודאי vadai that he is not considered
statements uttered while somebody is in this state are not he is
not considered to be a בר דעת bar daas or not considered
either he's not a בר דעת bar daas like בגברא begavra as
we would say, you know, or those statements are not considered to
be at all an expression of his will and therefore you do
not go ahead and...
Was there a sanity test that they administered?
No, it does not tell you how you know if he has
קורדייקוס kordaikos or not and when you know he's over it. That
is that was not indicated. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says
like this: אמר ריש לקיש: Amar Reish Lakish: כותבין ונותנין גט לאלתר.
kosvin venosnin get le'altar. You give the גט get immediately, even while
he's in the middle of this קורדייקוס kordaikos fit, based on what
he said before he had it. רבי יוחנן אמר: Rebbi Yochanan amar:
אין כותבין אלא לכשישתפה. ein kosvin ela lichsheyishtafe. No,
you wait till he gets better. Now, he does not mean after
he gets better you have to check with him again, because then
the משנה Mishna wouldn't have said anything. He means you give it
after he's better, but you don't have to ask him again, meaning
the retraction when he had קורדייקוס kordaikos didn't mean anything. But the
גט get cannot be given when he's in that state of mind
because רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan says is a גט get cannot be
given when a person is not a בר דעת. bar daas. So
if a because for me to do an act, right, for the
husband to give the גט get himself, he would have to be
a בר דעת. bar daas. For the שליח shaliach to give it
and represent the husband, right, the husband have to be in a
state where the husband could deliver the גט get himself, right? Otherwise,
you know, if the husband is not is not is not considered
of his own capacity, I mean you're right, like in American law,
you would have somebody you would make somebody your power of attorney
so that דווקא davka if you did become, you know, incapacitated, that
person is empowered to make decisions for you. But that's but that's
not how שליחות shlichus is understood. שליחות shlichus is understood that that
I am doing it sort of through the שליח. shaliach.
So I have to be...
Like if a person becomes paralyzed? כל מילתא דאיהו לא מצי עביד
שליח לא מצי עביד. Kol milsa de'ihu lo matzi avid shaliach lo
matzi avid. The basic principle is כל מילתא דאיהו לא מצי עביד
שליח לא מצי עביד. kol milsa de'ihu lo matzi avid shaliach lo
matzi avid. Anything you couldn't do your שליח shaliach can't. If he
became paralyzed? No, no, so it doesn't mean not can't do because
of a physical ability. It means can't do because you're not considered
to have the halachic capacity to do it. But that's a good
point and the גמרא Gemara is actually going to get to that.
Okay, but something that you don't have the halachic capacity to do,
somebody cannot have more power than the person that they represent. Okay,
so that's what רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan says. At least that's what
רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan is saying. We're going to see what the
how the גמרא Gemara develops this.
You wait until
you wait until he gets better. מאי טעמא דריש לקיש? Mai ta'ama
deReish Lakish? Schwartzer, reason of ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish. דקתני אין בדברים
אחרונים כלום. Deksani ein bidevarim acharonim klum. His last words mean nothing,
which basically means you just go as if nothing happened.
Let's see the גמרא Gemara develop it, okay? Hold on a second.
You just so ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says it sounds like the
משנה Mishna you just go merrily on your way. רבי יוחנן אמר
לך: Rebbi Yochanan amar lach: אין בדברים אחרונים כלום. ein bidevarim acharonim
klum. No, his last words don't mean anything means דכי מיתפיל dechi
mispil that when he gets healed, when he gets better, לא צריך
למהדר ומימלך ביה. lo tzarich lemehadar umimalach bei. You don't have to
go and ask him again, you know, do you still want to
give a גט get to your wife? You don't have to ask
him again. His retraction meant absolutely nothing. That is correct. But even
though the retraction meant nothing, ולעולם אין כותבין אלא לכשישתפה, ul'olam ein
kosvin ela lichsheyishtafe, the writing has to be done when he's of
the right mind. Okay, so במאי קמיפלגי, bemai kamipalgi, what's this debate
about? ריש לקיש מדמי ליה לישן. Reish Lakish midamei lei leyoshen. ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish says it's like somebody sleeping. ורבי יוחנן מדמי ליה
לשוטה. veRebbi Yochanan midamei lei leshote.
And רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan says it's like a שוטה, shote, somebody
who is like never of right mind, somebody who is really of,
you know, of not sound mind. רבי יוחנן נמי... Rebbi Yochanan nami...
so the גמרא Gemara says, so is this person, right, you can
give a גט get when a person is sleeping, right? So this
is, you know, in Brisk language this was the language would be
like בגברא, begavra, right? Is this person a גברא gavra of a
בר דעת? bar daas? Is this person like is his personal status
that he is a person of, you know, of right mind and
therefore a גט get can be given on his behalf or is
he not a person of right mind? So somebody who is a
שוטה shote that actually has
a mental ailment, then is not considered to be a person of
right mind and you can't give a גט get on their behalf.
Somebody who's asleep is, they're just currently not conscious, they're not in
control of their דעת daas right now, but בגברא begavra they're a
person of right mind. What about a person who has a passing
seizing fit? Okay, is that like somebody who's asleep, basically בגברא begavra
he's in his right mind, the fit will pass and he'll be
totally back to where he was, right? Or is that no, this
is different because he's like awake and can't think straight and whatever.
Let's see how the גמרא Gemara frames how to go either way.
So let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says and ריש
לקיש...
Reish Lakish... so רבי יוחנן נמי לידמיה לישן. Rebbi Yochanan nami lidmyei
leyoshen.
Why not say that it's similar to a person who's sleeping? ישן
לא מחוסר מעשה. Yoshen lo mechussar ma'aseh. No, the person sleeping isn't
lacking any act to be done, will just wake up normally. So
clearly that doesn't change their personal status as a בר דעת. bar
daas. האי מחוסר מיתא. Hai mechussar maysa. This person, the fit of
קורדייקוס kordaikos won't pass naturally. It has to be treated. And therefore
that defines his personal status. He's going to be he's going to
be in this state until we treat him. וריש לקיש נמי לידמיה
לשוטה. uReish Lakish nami lidmyei leshote. So ריש לקיש Reish Lakish say
that it's like a שוטה, shote, somebody who is
really...
Right, why doesn't he?
Right, why doesn't he? Let him, let him compare it to a
שוטה. shota. Why doesn't he compare it to a שוטה? shota? It
is true this won't, the guy won't get out of this naturally.
No, because שוטה לא סמי בידן. shota lo sami b'yadan. The שוטה,
shota, we don't have the healing in our hand, we don't have
the remedy. So שוטה shota is a going to have that as
a permanent state, or certainly nothing that we can control, he won't
get out of naturally and we have no way of controlling. So
that really defines his personal status. האי סמי בידן, Hai sami b'yadan,
this, we have the, we have what, the treatment? What's the treatment?
What do you think we've been doing for the last two דפין?
dappin? בישרא סומקא אגומרי, bisra sumka agumre, right? It's the lean meat
on the coals וחמרא מרקא v'chamra marka and the diluted wine. Now
you see why we had to have that earlier גמרא Gemara so
we understand the debate of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש.
Resh Lakish. That occurs to me. In other words, all that stuff
was brought
right,
so you could now see that we really have a way of
healing this. Okay, so I think it's a fascinating question, right? At
what stage do we say that a person's sort of current state
of mind, you know, sort of defines their personal status? Or do
we see this as like just a passing state? You know, it's
a state, but it's not a status. It doesn't define, you know,
who they are as a legal entity.
Right, but halachically, the גמרא Gemara can bring this מחלוקת machloket around
that conceptualization because they can assert that this cure
works, works, right, which
if we reject it, what happens to the halachic conceptualization?
Right, I agree with you. I think we've established the idea that
we know what we're talking about in terms of cures, I agree.
Applies to all the implications for all those right, I agree with
you,
I think
that's I think that that is correct.
What I didn't understand a bit better is this all happens sort
of at the same time, right? He he said it and then
and then you know got this
ten minutes later he was seized with his קורדייקוס, Kordiakos,
it could be a year later, it's just sort of delayed. Do
we say they could still write it now because he had this
whole year that they could have written it while
he was a בר דעת? Bar Da'at? Sure, as long as he
doesn't retract it. Yeah, that's the ציווי tzivuy still standing. There's no
expiration date on the ציווי.
tzivuy. Can he also give it now? In other words, he said
write it and give it.
Yeah, but they can't give it if if they waited a year
to do it and now the guy has קורדייקוס, Kordiakos, they can't
do it now. Right, while they are now writing the גט, Get,
they are representing the husband and if the husband is not seen
as being a בר דעת, Bar Da'at, as a personal status of
a person of right mind, then they cannot write a גט Get
on his behalf. Even though before he could have, right?
Yeah, but if this person gets קורדייקוס Kordiakos and never recovers, according
to רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan the גט Get never goes forward.
Exactly, absolute, exactly correct. Yeah, okay. So the, yep, so the גמרא
Gemara says okay as you could imagine this has real practical implications.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says ומי אמר רבי יוחנן הכי? Umi
amar Rabbi Yochanan hachi? Does רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan really say that
you can't write the גט Get while he has this state? ואמר
רב יהודה אמר שמואל, V'amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda says in the name of שמואל, Shmuel, שחט בו שנים או
רוב שנים, shachat bo shenayim o rov shenayim, somebody who had both
his trachea and esophagus slit or the majority of them slit, so
he's obviously going to die, ורמז
ואמר כתבו גט לאשתי, v'ramaz v'amar kitvu get l'ishti, but he indicated
to write a גט Get for his wife so his wife wouldn't
have to worry about ייבום Yibum presumably because she's either going to
be an אלמנה almanah or a גרושה, grusha, better be a גרושה,
grusha, הרי אלו יכתבו ויתנו, harei elu yichtevu v'yitnu, okay fine, they
can write it, he's you know of right mind, he's not dead
yet, so even though he's going to die, as long as they
can get it done in time. ותניא, V'tanya, we learned in a
ברייתא, Baraisa, וראוהו מגויד, v'rauhu meguyod, if they saw somebody like dismembered,
או צלוב, o tzaluv, or crucified, על הצליבה, al hatzliva, on a
cross, ורמז ואמר כתבו גט לאשתי, v'ramaz v'amar kitvu get l'ishti, and
he indicated to write a גט Get to his wife, הרי אלו
יכתבו ויתנו, harei elu yichtevu v'yitnu, so they can write. Now what
type of a question is that? So תוספות Tosafot says the only
question must be that the גמרא Gemara thinks that you can give
it right as long as the guy hasn't totally died, but the
גמרא Gemara seems like by the end of this stage the person
is going to not be in his right mind, right? After this
type of a trauma or whatever, even if right now he's in
his right mind when he commands it, by the time you get
around to writing it and giving it, you have to be afraid
that he's not going to be of right mind. Right? Otherwise it's
not at all like related to the discussion.
Just showing symptoms
and still be a בר דעת? Bar Da'at?
Well, the גמרא's Gemara question is that why aren't we concerned that
when it's being given he's not in his right mind? Because by
the time you get around to giving it, now the question is
תוספות Tosafot says this is really a question to ריש לקיש Resh
Lakish as well because this is לא סמי בידן, lo sami b'yadan,
right? So the גמרא Gemara says תוספות Tosafot says fine, but it's
more obvious question to רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. But let's anyway see,
the answer is going to be what?
We suggested that before, we say כתבו kitvu and not תנו t'nu
and they say because he was so confused by the situation he
forgot to say give it.
Yeah, but that's what the ציווי tzivuy meant, but here the question
is what's taking place when it's being given. And if the person
has gone out of his mind by the time it's being given,
then you've got this problem. But the גמרא's Gemara answer is going
to be he hasn't gone out of his mind, so let's just
continue reading.
In all those stories
we have is, I know, so don't worry, לשכיב מרע. l'shechiv mera.
I know, I
know, I know, I know. Well,
it's a little bit different if you have, if you have an
illness, if you're dying of poison that you could be of your
right mind whereas somebody's being dismembered or crucified or whatever,
ויוצא קולר v'yotze kolar and שכיב מרע. shechiv mera.
I got it. Well let's read the next line. Okay? The גמרא,
Gemara, don't worry, the גמרא's Gemara gonna say, the גמרא's Gemara gonna
say הכא השתא, Hacha hashta, what type of a comparison is it?
חזינן דעתיה צילותא. Chazinan da'atei tziluta. There we'll assume that they have
clear mind, clear, you know, their mind is clear, he, that כחישותא
דאתחלו ביה kechishuta de'atchalu bei and even if a person is like
thrashing around or whatever till the very end, it's just because of
the weakness if they're not able to speak or indicate towards the
very end, it's just because of their, they're weak, you know, or
their body, they're dying, but not because that they're not of right
mind. הכא Hacha in this case דעתיה שגישתא, da'atei shagishta, the person's
mind is confused, he. So basically all these cases as Johnson correctly
said of a person in the process of dying and having a
גט get written, we're not concerned that they're, they're not going to
be of right mind. Okay? So they're not relevant for our discussion.
Right, because as a matter of halachically, you know, that was my
question before, if you're paralyzed, it's still...
Right, and correct. And the fact that somebody is physically not able
to give a גט get is not a problem of שליחות. shelichus.
שליחות Shelichus is not that you have to be physically able to
do it, it's that you have to be halachically able to do
it. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this: ומי אמר
שמואל הכי Umi amar Shmuel hachi did שמואל Shmuel really, did שמואל
Shmuel really
say that? Where's שמואל Shmuel again?
Oh, he was the one about שחט בו שנים או רוב שנים.
shachit bo shenayim o rov shenayim. ומי אמר שמואל הכי ואמר רב
יהודה אמר שמואל שחט בו שנים או רוב שנים וברח Umi amar
Shmuel hachi ve'amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel shachit bo shenayim o rov
shenayim ubarach and he ran away.
How's he doing that?
I don't know, anyway he was on a, he was on a
wagon, who knows? Okay. מעידים עליו Me'idim alav you can testify that
he's dead, you can assume basically he's dead and his wife can
remarry, so you see, so how can you write a גט? get?
So the גמרא Gemara thinks that that means as soon as his
throat is cut, he's already halachically dead. אי סלקא דעתך דחי הוא
I salka da'atach dechai hu if you think he's still halachically alive
so that you can write a גט get for his wife, אמאי
מעידים עליו, amai me'idim alav, why can you testify that he's dead?
That's what it says, obvious answer, גמרא Gemara says, is אמרי, amri,
no, you say חי הוא וסופו למות. chai hu vesofu lamut. He's
alive but you know he'll die, he'll be dead pretty soon. So
when it says you can testify for his wife, it doesn't tell
you how much time, maybe you need to wait a day, two
days, but you can definitely assume that he died soon after even
if you don't see him. But as long as you still see
him alive, he's halachically alive. אלא מעתה Ella me'ata says the גמרא,
Gemara, if that's true that he's definitely going to die, יהא גולה
על ידו, yehei goleh al yado, why if somebody accidentally does this
to a person, slits their throat, why does he not go into
exile if it's, you know... Because he's alive now. Well no, even
if he dies afterwards, well let's take a look. Says the גמרא
Gemara what?
He's making her a גרושה grusha instead of an אלמנה? almanah?
Yeah, to save her from יבום. yibum. The whole reason of doing
this, of writing a גט get as has been going on as
a theme from the beginning, writing a גט get before you die
so that the wife's a גרושה grusha not so that she doesn't
have to worry about יבום. yibum. Okay.
So אלא מה תניא, alama tanya, why do we teach in a
ברייתא, Baraita, שחט בו שנים או רוב שנים הרי זה אינו גולה.
shachit bo shenayim o rov shenayim harei zeh eino goleh. You do
not, the person does not go into exile. So we thought that
the reason was was that maybe he wouldn't definitely die or, but
now you're telling me he's definitely going to die, so why not
go into exile? So the גמרא Gemara says, איתמר עלה אמר רבי
אושעיא חיישינן שמא רוח בלבלתו. itmar alah amar Rabi Oshaya chaishinan shema
ruach bilbelato. No, he will definitely die, but there might be other
contributing factors. It might be that the
wind got into sort of the cut and actually sped up the
death. אי נמי הוא קירב את מיתתו I nami hu kirev et
mitato or that he actually himself because he was trembling and shaking
and you know whatever, he sped up his own death.
So meaning if you do this to somebody accidentally you never גולה?
goleh? I mean that's what we'll say.
Right. Basically we'll say, it definitely will happen, but there might be
other contributing factors once this is the case. מאי בינייהו, Mai beinaihu,
what would be a case you'd have one and not the other?
איכא בינייהו דשחטיה בבית דשישא, Ika beinaihu deshachatei be'veit de'shisha, that he
was slaughtered in a house of marble that no wind and air
could get into. ופרכס, Upirkas, and he shook. So the shaking might
be showing that he's doing it to himself, but it's not the
wind. אי נמי דשחטיה בברא I nami deshachatei be'bara outside ולא פרכס
velo pirkas and he didn't shake, so it could have been the
wind and not him. So if you wanted a scenario where it
was definitely not either of those, it would have had to be
a marble house where there was no shaking. Now, תוספות Tosafot points
out that a very important...
Natural shaking of a person?
Yeah, that contributes to the death. So probably what you're asking is,
really? How does somebody get off because of that? Obviously it was,
so תוספות Tosafot says, it's clear that if somebody did this intentionally
it would be murder and they would actually be executed. The fact
that because after you slaughtered him the wound got infected and it
sped it up a little bit, who cares? You know, the fact
that, you know, you did this mortal wound, that's why he died.
So the הלכה halacha is though that for גלות galus we have
a much narrower category of things of a person going into exile,
you know, if he's going up a ladder as opposed to down
a ladder, you know, a certain degree not too much שוגג shogeg
but not too much, you know, מזיד meizid like there's all these
narrow things. So that just says it's like a גזירת הכתוב. gezerat
hakatuv. It doesn't exactly explain why. The רב Rav had a, had
a brilliant explanation about why. He said that the difference is like
this, is that when, you know, the classic case of גלות galus
is one that we normally would halachically categorize as מתעסק, misasek, right?
The guy is just hammering, you know, like chopping wood and the
handle flies
and you
know and the, whatever, the head flies off, right? So that normally
is מתעסק. misasek. I mean imagine you were
doing that, you
know, you were at... Now not every case is like that when
a guy falls down a ladder and he hits the guy himself.
Okay, but anyway, I mean it might be a difference if it's
גופו gufo or כוחו, kocho, right, but anyway, I understand it. I
understand it. You're not chopping wood. You're just practicing with a hammer.
Anyway, so he says it's מתעסק. misasek. Now מתעסק misasek means it's
not your action, as opposed to a person willfully
commits an act of murder, then it's his action. Once it's his
action, he did a מעשה רציחה. ma'aseh retzichah. He did an act
to this guy which created a mortal wound that the guy is
going to die from. That's a מעשה רציחה ma'aseh retzichah and the
person is executed. But in the other case, there's no מעשה רציחה.
ma'aseh retzichah. The other case, we have to start in the opposite
direction. We say, a guy is dead here. You're to blame. You
didn't do an act of killing him, but you're to blame. So
once we have to work backwards, no,
your actions led to some events that happened but it's not considered
a מעשה ma'aseh because it's מתעסק. misasek. The whole point of מתעסק
misasek is that it doesn't relate to—it's not your action. So therefore
he says, so since you—you didn't do the act—an act of murder,
an act of killing him—the person died, and now we have to—don't
distract him, I'm trying to explain something—the person died, and now we
have to retroactively say, and now we have to say after the
fact, we see the guy is dead, you're to blame. So to
say you're to blame, then as long as there's some other thing
that was a contributing factor, we can't as easily draw the line
of connection. You know, we can't say, well, this is all as
a result of you. Well, it's not all as a result of
me. It was partly other things as well. So the sort of—the
fact that we're not starting from you having done an act of
murder. The guy doesn't have to die yet to be an act
of murder. You have to do an act to a person that
mortally wounds them, right? But here, it wasn't a מעשה, ma'aseh, so
because we have to work in sort of the reverse direction, therefore
these other things can be mitigating factors.
So even though things logically happen naturally? Yeah, this would still be
a mitigating
factor, apparently.